Contact

www.linkedin.com/in/wolfganggruen (LinkedIn)

Top Skills

XML

JSON

Kubernetes

Languages

English (Native or Bilingual)
German (Native or Bilingual)
Spanish (Elementary)

Certifications

AWS Integrated Services

Software Processes and Agile Practices

Deep Dive into Amazon Simple Storage Service (S3)

Introduction to Amazon Elastic MapReduce (EMR)

AWS Architecture

Wolfgang Gruen

Principal Systems Architect Cloud and Engineering Leader Ashburn, Virginia, United States

Summary

Accomplished systems architect, leader and software engineer with a broad experience in cloud architecture, software development, product definition and technical project leadership with global teams.

Known for being the go-to person for complex analysis and person of last resort for the most challenging customer issues.

My interest is in Cloud Architecture, Microservices, Machine and Deep Learning.

Experience

ST Engineering iDirect 16 years 7 months

Principal Systems Architect - Cloud November 2022 - Present (1 year 1 month)

Herndon, Virginia, United States

As a systems architect, I am responsible for the Next Generation Satellite Hub deployment, integration with the Next Gen Network Management System, integration of performance enhancing and 3rd party products.

Principal and Architect and Release Lead July 2019 - October 2022 (3 years 4 months)

Herndon, Virginia, United States

As an engineering leader, I am responsible for product quality, release readiness, defining a minimal viable product, release planning, writing and negotiating of statements of work, and other aspects of projects with globally dispersed, highly skilled teams.

As an architect, I am influencing concepts and architectures across engineering

I engage with product owners, scrum masters, engineering leads, architects and senior management across organizations to ensure we cover all aspects needed for a high quality software release.

Led a project about unification of tools across our global organizations.

Supported the most urgent customer issues for the private cloud and infrastructure

Improved scalable for infrastructure software to achieve the next level of scalability requirements

Influenced architecture and concepts and diligently helped finding the best solution with stakeholders across many organizations

Principal Software Engineer - Customer Success February 2018 - June 2019 (1 year 5 months) Herndon, VA

Supported the most complex field issues for the Satellite Hub for the Velocity platform.

Prototyped a Satellite Hub as micro services, using Docker and Kubernetes

Negotiated incremental deliveries and deadlines directly with the customer and provided the software solutions for most urgent and complex scalability issues

Senior Software Engineering Manager - QoS June 2013 - January 2018 (4 years 8 months)

Managed a self-organizing, global Agile software development team of crossfunctional engineers for new feature development for the Satellite Hub for the Velocity platform.

Software Engineering Manager - PRIVATE CLOUD June 2011 - May 2013 (2 years)

Managed a team of software developers and contractors, including off-shore for the Infrastructure team for the Satellite Hub for the Velocity platform. Designed and architected high available scalable private cloud in an Agile fashion.

Incubated new features, while co-authoring requirements with system architects and created high level design documents.

Senior Software Engineer - Infrastructure May 2007 - May 2011 (4 years 1 month)

Developed scalability enhancements for the Satellite Hub software for the Evolution platform.

Led multiple projects to successful delivery as technical lead.

CACI International Inc Senior Software Developer and Team Lead 2003 - 2007 (4 years)

Developed software for the DOD Standard Procurement System. Supervised a team of seven developers.

Patton Electronics Co. Senior Software Engineer 2000 - 2003 (3 years)

Develop software for a 96 port dial-up T1 internet access device. Gained expertise in UNIX V kernel, TCP/IP, OSPF, IP protocols and routing protocols.

Education

Hochschule Mannheim

Master's degree, Computer and Software Engineering / Telecommunications · (1995 - 1999)